So you're very lucky.
People are about to hear Patrick Debois
Patrick is the AI Product Engineer at Tessl
and the curator of AINativedev.io.
Did you also have a hand in the app?
No, no.
That wasn't. Yes.
Sorry. Oh.
He's upstairs. Right? Okay.
Known as the father of DevOps,
Coined and termed the first organized DevOps day
in Ghent in 2009, and coauthor
of DevOps Handbook.
This was generated by an LLM.
Yeah.
I can tell by the long dash.
Anyway, today he's going to be talking to us about coding.
Agents don't scale themselves, and neither do your teams.
The rise of Agent and Abels.
Give it up for Patrick.
Thank you for coming.
Disclaimer this talk was first started in on Friday.
So it's a brand new talk.
Basically because the guy stole all my thunder on the calc.
So I had to come up with a new talk.
So it's a little bit experimental, but we get through that.
So he here has kind of like the struggle of scaling
agent coding within their organization. Who
has to deal with that problem.
Why kind of people. Right. Cool.
So development is changing.
And I think the best phrase to say is we're not building the thing.
We're building the thing that builds the thing.
That's kind of the new mentality and left and right kind of accurate the program.
So there's a little bit of a sprinkle of context that you might hear it in skills,
a little bit of harness engineering that is in there, but it is
pieces of the puzzle that are
largely technology pieces right now.
But I'm going to talk at like, what does it mean to use those things?
So one of the things is everybody's reinventing the wheel,
which is great with a new technology coming about
because you're all learning, but it's not sustainable every time.
First, DevOps.
Everybody was building their own deploys, kind of, you know, cloud.
Everybody was building their own S3.
That is not sustainable, right?
That's not what we want to go for.
But, you know, enablement.
And you all know the term developer enablement.
It doesn't happen by itself.
You have a team for that.
You have people that kind of actively nurture that within your org.
And that is the job that I wanted to describe, not about how you become
a better agentic coding per se, but how do you scale this out?
And the good news is you already know how, right?
Which is and you'll see that in the talk.
Everything that's good for humans that we've been advocating
for years on good engineering practices is actually good for agents.
And what's good for agents seems to be good for people, right?
Because maybe it's because the LLMs have been buried on our behavior,
and maybe that's that.
But maybe we got some pieces, right.
And it's not just about vibe coding that, hey,
I build an app, but how do I make the app sustainable?
Work, secure all those pieces.
And that's where engineering kicks in again.
So this probably could be a
two hour talk, but I got like 20 minutes left.
We're going to enable the agents.
That's what a lot of people talk about.
I want to talk briefly also like what do you do to enable the team.
What goes into the platform and how do you think about this piece
in your organization.
So first piece enable the agents.
How do you make it work?
Like DevOps
we've come up with a new term the AI product engineer.
It wasn't enough that we call them AI engineers because that was confusing
as AI and the product is the AI for software.
All of a sudden we have a new term the product engineer.
Hey, their customer focused Shinar deaths have been customer focused.
You know nothing.
But the nice thing for me is it's another silo pasta that kind of requirements.
I figure out what we need to build and that how to build.
It is kind of blending into work, which is not
now the way that I want people to think.
And I mentioned like build the thing that builds the thing.
One of the mindset challenges that people have is
even if the agent gets things wrong, they jump in and they correct a mistake.
What a really should be doing is improving the system
that builds the code and improves that, so they don't have to do it again.
So it's not about fix the code and fix the system.
And a lot of system engineers and platform people, they think in system mentality.
And that's why it's also quite natural to kind of think in those terms.
It's for me right now in the industry still the like
one of the predominant mistakes
is that you still go in and jump in and correct and take over.
The mentality should change to fix the system and have the agenda flow to that.
So I mentioned it like what good looks like.
Claude learned that we should have
planning before doing something.
We should have testing to see what are the agent
did something well or not, or what do we pull the trick
and change functionality that we didn't want?
I always say, like, I never knew
I would see the day that developers would write start writing documentation
on their own, but they learned that actually by writing
specs or whatever you call it, context, all of a sudden things become better.
And then if you add observability, the agents can actually
kind of observe themselves and improve, right?
Nothing new is just rehashed with the new mindset.
It's not all the agents doing that stuff,
okay.
So that reusability comes into
not changing the context and the problems you think about.
Reusable specs kind of make that and that goes to both harness components.
Tools make them reusable.
Now, it's very tempting to not listen to whatever happens in the production.
And yes, as a dev, you've never been used to like being told, like, you know,
the only thing that matters is how your end user is having issues.
And those have been signals that we've been trying to educate that
like whenever you see a signal
that is not performing well, change the system and improve that.
So that is how you have to think about that.
Smaller tasks.
No surprise there.
Like big task.
The agent goes in all directions.
That's true.
And then you measure actually before that happens.
The funny
part is everybody builds their own context.
While I have my CLAUDE.md and you see the copy and paste
being told on the internet, like use this, use that.
Not sustainable. Right.
So what you want to do is
you want to standardize like a library within your team, within your code base.
No, shared kernels
shouldn't tell you this,
but we didn't test all we have now, 5 or 6 harnesses being built,
which is great for learning, but probably only a few should survive
after that is done because that is useful.
You have to maintain the specs.
It's not a one thing.
It will change, it will not be up to date.
And eventually another problem that we're facing is
as we're putting more pieces, like you go to your triage ticket system,
you're kind of maybe reviews your customer database.
All those pieces have not been set up well for access control.
It's a running problem that we have.
We're getting better at that. There's
maybe some new specs that come around, but this is what it gets hard.
So we've learned about this kind of just limit
the kind of the blast wall of everything that you're doing for agents.
So that's the same thing as we would do before for users.
If there's one mindset change
that I want, almost like, what do you tell a developer
right now in the agentic coding that's already agentic coding?
I would stress this
every time you did something.
Think about not repeating this again.
And this was the mentality also for DevOps automation.
Like whatever we do, it's not it works on my machine.
It works with my agent.
It works like, you know, my snowflake machine or anything.
It is make it repeatable.
And that kind of gets you in a motion of improvement.
I hope no surprises there so far, right?
But what about the team?
There was the team lead that.
Now what is their job?
So they're not only helping the humans but they're helping the agents as well.
Now because our team members. Right.
Kind of that mentality of going through is important
because basically what I think they're going
to be like accountable for is
we're in the past and that silly portal developers performance
and kind of like what they deliver and the quality and all those pieces.
But increasingly it's also what their agents, how
well they are, they are performing because they're part of that system as well.
You can say this is the quality of your own, like a microservice system.
This is also your ownership of whatever piece that you're building.
But now the tools that you're building to build the thing is also
a piece of your responsibility that you should be tracking as well.
What's good for you?
I is good for you.
Clear goals.
You want to have token spend go up through the roof.
Just tell it something vague, right?
Want to run it overnight and see what it did?
All the things that it spent.
Not useful, right?
Sharing the context and kind of no surprises.
Like keep it like predictable what you're going
with the goal that you're going for.
Now some of the new practices on a try.
That's kind of what I'm like, challenging myself with.
I could tell you a generic transformation story in a company
and say, well, developers need to use more.
I let's do a hackathon, give everybody a tool.
Great.
Like, you know, we're self graduated ourselves.
But what is changing?
And here's a few kind of new things like her coding.
There's almost like a pair of context writing.
What's your style.
What do you put in what is important.
So kind of that is team dynamics.
What is the definition of Dawn is that the code is going out
or was there more to it?
Is that the agent doing its best and how that's performing
that becomes part of your definition of done.
So you need a kind of metric.
And one of the metrics that I really like
is how many turns does an agent
need to do to do the right thing?
If you start measuring that, you're actually looking at how efficient
am I feeling?
How efficient is my harness to make that a better optimization in that, much like
you would look at your team members, how do you make them work together?
Well?
And some teams similar to their retro how did we work
is how did our agents work.
And they do that at the end and then they feed back into the next cycle.
So very similar, but quite concrete of what
people are doing now in those kind of team dynamics.
The velocity
metrics are great, but there's more to it, right?
There's rework.
There's like the turns of the things.
You've got to educate people because not
everybody is an excellent writer in skills and prose.
So that is education, much like you would do
training for people, regular coding,
and one of the kind of hard
challenges is they used to be the coding rockstar.
You kind of have to translate them almost into your
the amazing context provider that tells the agents,
which is the great like Agent Whisperer, right?
Because that is what you're aiming like, want to get them into.
Not everybody wants to do this, so want to deal with the code.
But it's also a great way to have almost the the skeptics.
As I said, AI can't do what I do.
All right.
Maybe you can write down what it is you do that we can make the agents better.
Right.
And that kind of shared library has also kind of a little bit of a challenge.
If you put it in the repo and it's like, yeah, it's in the repo, but
you know, it's the common grounds which has pro and cons, like
who has the ownership of certain pieces of libraries of skills and other pieces.
So if I want to get, I mean
a new my chest team leaders should think about like
my agents are team members to how do you find the goal, the KPI,
how do I measure the performance,
how I make them play well with my team and all those pieces?
Everything you already know, but kind of on a different level
now with the agents.
All right, let's get this out.
We got like one developer, few developers team
enable a platform scale is how it came to work.
It's a very common pattern.
Every time a new technology, we had the agile team,
we had the DevOps team, we have the athletic enablement team.
It's the incubation team that starts to change.
And then maybe we mimic that into your next team, into your next team.
And eventually we think, hey,
maybe we should like put them everything in a shared layer.
And we don't have everybody doing the boilerplate over and over again.
That's that.
So these people
built for the team that builds the thing that builds the thing.
Right.
And I think they're the natural people
who will think about optimizing the whole
great I got skills, but how do they work together across teams?
Can they be reused across teams?
I write my CLAUDE.md, but can I put pieces of that?
I have a harness and a pipeline.
Can I make that reusable?
So that's their mindset.
The other mindset that we don't have yet enough
is and I've been asking for AI coding vendors
for like many times I go to a booth.
It's like, all right, you're great.
So you're doing getting all the feedback.
Agents are improving.
Do you do any learning of things it does in prod?
We don't have a question for that.
There's no requests by people learning about this.
And you end up being in another group
of vendors who talks about AI within the platform.
And they do all the observability,
but combining both is apparently the same mistake
as we're not learning from what was put into the wild.
We think putting the wild was within our test environment that the test run.
But it was not about what went into the coding.
So the other piece I do
is, hey, I need a memory.
I need other pieces that all the agents share a backbone.
That's what they're going to provide.
Not every team is going to build that infrastructure right now.
That's what they do because they're experimenting the learning.
It's okay.
But eventually that will sink somewhere centrally.
So what does a good platform look like?
What's good for people?
It's good for AI self-serve.
If you think about like somebody
going through hoops of copying skills and so on.
They just want to simply pull in the right.
That friction needs to be very nice.
You want to put the best practice in place.
Maybe we have some security scanning all those pieces
that if they have to do it, they have to do it all themselves.
You want to make that easy path of something they pull from that says,
or when they push their context monitoring.
Right.
Agent observability of what
your coding agents are doing across the whole organization.
Do you want every team to spin up their own kind of monitoring and observability?
No. Just use the central tool because now we can find insights and learn
what is missing
from context of what are pieces that are missing that we should address.
And finally, maybe some new skills for or have a new tool that addresses
that central view is used because it will kind of transcend
the knowledge across the organization and not just your team.
And then putting the guardrails in place.
So this brings things to, well, we had a registry to
put our code so we can have a registry for our skills.
And we want it to be versioned.
And we will have a registry for MCP skills harnesses, agents, agent pipelines.
It doesn't matter.
It's the same pattern discoverability somewhere central, reusable, self-serve.
To pull this in,
we'll have
gateways, one of the first pieces that product people put in place
when using AI is a gateway and an MCP and so on.
For coding.
We're like, you know, we can't wait.
But once you start putting a harness of agents that work together,
you say, no, no, no, we need an entity gateway.
We need the observability.
We need all those pieces in place and the evolve platform do that centrally
and then ownership.
Right.
When you're in a platform team, there's kind of this red post
that everybody shares to your repositories usually.
And then there's the one that kind of get abandoned and nobody knows.
Right.
Remember the time that we had to like by tools
that actually searches or repos, are they still active?
Are they still maintained.
Who owns this is the same piece there as well.
One of the challenges is much like,
hey, you should write tests.
That's a great idea.
Sure, I'll do it after my project when I have time.
It's the same experience.
Let me right evolve.
Well, you know, I'll do that after the project when I have, like,
things making that easy.
Making that self-serve is definitely something your platform team
can help with.
Now one of the challenges, I think it was mentioned this morning,
I built a skill that's great.
I want to share that with somebody else.
They'll look at it.
It's like, yeah, like it for 99%.
Let me kind of change that one bit and then it becomes a fork.
That same mentality is like,
you want to roll your own, but you want to make it extensible, right?
So you want to make sure that everybody's contributing to that central place.
And then you need to have a way, not just to test it when it's the mind
within the mind of the developers, but you also need to do the maintenance.
Is it still secure? Is it still optimizing?
When I change, the model is similar to one.
An external kind of
company changes the API and you didn't change anything incurred,
but all of a sudden your tests are failing.
This is the same thing that you're trying to do.
But now for skills, for harnesses and pieces there as well.
As long as you don't have that testing
and that repeatable thing in place, you will have that same problem.
And so the no ownership of shared components
is that whenever somebody pushes is that you have to ask, who owns this?
Who's going to maintain this, who has the budget to do this?
That is kind of the question. If you go from there
and I think their mindset should be
you're really, really special person,
but the way you work isn't and I'm sorry to break it to you.
Right. So
I don't know how many people told me this DevOps thing.
Yeah, we can't do it anymore.
Org like we're special.
You don't understand how we work.
Guess what? After a while, everybody could do it right.
That mentality of breaking this is the same thing with pipelines.
Well, you know what I you know,
it was there like let me compile a kernel because I know exactly what I need.
Who cares. Like, you know, it's a VM.
It spins up. It's great. Right.
I'm not saying you shouldn't think, but it should be more deliberate
where you kind of put the customization in, place them up.
You always see this with people saying like, oh,
I really need to have my coding agent really fast.
And then they guess what? Like, oh, you know, it runs in the background.
I don't care that much.
I want to have it, like produce the right results.
Not that it's like instant feedback so I can reply to it in real time.
So kind of that is looking out for those things.
Last layer
enabled the organization. So
more towards the VP engineering.
So okay they're top build
the org that builds for the teams that builds the team.
And I think this is probably
the broadest enablement role of them all.
And right now we're kind of struggling.
What did we put in place.
We give everybody the tools Ray okay.
And now what.
All right let's monitor spend of everybody.
And it's kind of challenging in that.
So I think we're previous job.
And I'm not saying it's going to be replaced.
They should still hire engineers.
They should ship reliable and it's sustainable pace.
But I think they need to work on
how do you enable the system.
Is that people creating tickets
flowing easily into what the agent has access to,
maybe the platform
team cannot look at until a VP comes in and say,
let me unlock kind of these groups and you have to kind of work together,
which is quite two children on a playground, but
you get the idea.
What does a good organization look like?
What's good for people? It's good for you.
I'm clear. This is my piece.
We're responsible.
You're going to prove this because ownership drives improvement.
And otherwise it's just could fall between the cracks.
If team A needs to do this and TB,
it needs to be that you're aligning kind of the direction of the different teams.
And that's your work on doing this.
And the sustainable pace is well, if one team is completely over
producing all the rest
and they can't look at all the changes, you kind of have to balance
which team is still struggling, which team needs investment in education,
which team kind of need to maybe have some help
from the platform team to kind of set up their whole new environment.
And then you want to, of course, worry about the cost as well.
So kind of putting that like
investment clear that it is beyond
iron buying licenses for all my tools.
Like what is the investment on education?
What is the investment
of kind of improving the pipeline, monitoring how well they're performing?
And how much do I care about that?
That is the tipping point between just saying, here's the problem of tools.
Run with it.
I don't know.
Between I care, I set a direction.
This is where I will measure you as a productivity.
Like how much is it redoing the same thing?
How much efficiency are you getting through there as well?
And then you put the governance in place.
I think it was mentioned already a few times.
The skills, the context.
Who gets access to what do you mandate that there have to be security scans?
Do you kind of see whether you only allowed
kind of almost like a proof skills,
almost like when we did with registries, you're only allowed to use these
because they have been fitted
and the other ones we're not doing, but we can bring them in.
We have a process
of bringing external skills internally and kind of bring them out to that.
And then we set the KPIs.
And I know this sounds a little bit vague, and that's kind of what I'm working on.
Like if you any any kind of specific advice
more tailored to context and all those pieces, that's kind of what
I'm trying to describe on the enablement instead of the fake things.
But we do know that you want to have a KPI for agent quality as well,
instead of only the quality of what is your measurement,
because it's an integral part of your system.
As usual,
struggle to say, I'm going to invest with this,
but the business isn't care
because you need to have return now,
so that's why you need to make it visible.
You need to make the pain visible.
And that was the same with security.
If you can't show how many vulnerabilities you're having, how much that risk
is telling that you can't actually
start justifying the return on investment only by saying
we're are we to x ten x I don't know, it looks good to me.
So that's not the mentality that we're going for.
So we want to avoid the quick Wins award and actually make that enablement team.
Much like a platform team, it requires an investment to go for.
Unfortunately,
there is no playbook.
And that's kind of the challenging part is like,
okay, we're all learning while we go.
And it's a very kind of unsatisfactory thing.
But I think layer by layer, that's the improvement.
So if you're already
set the step on the investment, you'll go through it and collapse it.
The mental model that I usually use is that if you have a barrel
and there are all the sides that are hold together,
if you do any automation.
In the past we developed,
if you have one piece of the barrel
that is very low,
the water will pour through there.
So I think the trick is you go on step by step on all the phases you improve part
of the governance, part of the automation, and you go that by layer instead.
If you automate everything and you don't have your governance in place,
that doesn't make sense.
And that's my pet peeve.
Continuous integration,
continuous delivery.
And I think with all the context that we're accumulating and the tools
were basically learning how to do our craft better and to learn
how fast we can do things. And.
In a world where it's almost
important to swap in and swap out
new technology as they become like a business edge,
you have to think about like, how fast can I adopt something new?
It's where continuous delivery was.
How can I deliver?
The existing may be more stable and like in that way, but right now
it is about accumulating knowledge within the org, across all the teams,
how your business is going to get better and build better and more reliable tools.
And for me, that is the step of continuous learning.
I'm working on this side.
Yes, it's on the test, but what I actually do is I have an agent.
Of course I have it
that looks at all the social posts
and tries to distill those into patterns.
Now, there are challenges because there's vendors who say,
this is how you do things,
which I'm trying to find a system that ignores the vendors.
But sometimes vendors are good because they have a good idea.
But I try to also find multiple sources about doing the same thing.
And when I find that
the challenge that is, are they just referring to the same article
like Brigida, it's like, hey, this is how you do all the things.
So I have to find out, like what is their thinking?
Is there a similarity in that?
So I'm trying to automate this and it's basically a research tool for me.
And I hope it's interesting for you as well to just find what people are doing
in the industry, because I think surveys right now are just too slow.
You can't wait until everybody says like, oh, you know, we're we're adapting.
We're just on Colette or Copilot. All good.
And that's it.
So in a nutshell, that's what I would say is an agent enablement.
If you're interested in kind of sharing, maybe some of your stories,
what you learned, how you framed, how you help, kind of the mindset change.
How do you think it's changing your iTunes ceremonies?
How do you think about the problem?
How do you find it to maybe your CFO?
I love to hear your stories, and if you want
to have the slides, connect with me on LinkedIn and I'll happily
share my flights in exchange for feedback, because that's what good developers do.
Thank you very much.